<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of King Charles I from the declaration of Mr. Alexander Henderson ... upon his death-bed : with a further defence of the King's holy book : to which is annex'd some short remarks upon a vile book, call'd Ludlow no lyar : with a defence of the King from the Irish Rebellion / by Rich. Hollingworth.</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12498577</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12498577</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 670:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of King Charles I from the declaration of Mr. Alexander Henderson ... upon his death-bed : with a further defence of the King's holy book : to which is annex'd some short remarks upon a vile book, call'd Ludlow no lyar : with a defence of the King from the Irish Rebellion / by Rich. Hollingworth.</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by R. Tayler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697. --  Ludlow no lyar.</term>
               <term>Henderson, Alexander, 1583?-1646. --  Declaration of Mr. Alexand. Henderson.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62608:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF King Charles I. From the <hi>Declaration</hi> of M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> ALEXANDER HENDERSON, (Principal Miniſter of the Word of God at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and Chief Commiſſioner from the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the Parliament and Synod of <hi>England</hi>) Upon his <hi>DEATH-BED:</hi> WITH A Further DEFENCE of the <hi>KING</hi>'s Holy Book.</p>
            <p>To which is Annex'd Some Short <hi>Remarks</hi> upon a Vile Book, call'd, <hi>Ludlow no Lyan:</hi> With A Defence of the KING from the Iriſh Rebellion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Rich. Hollingworth,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Tayler</hi> by <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:62608:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED, <hi>July,</hi> 28th. 1692. <hi>Rob. Midgley.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62608:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, THE MARCHIONESS of <hi>Carmarthen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Defence of Good and Innocent Men, and the Vindicating of their Memories, from thoſe baſe and barbarous Aſperſions they are many times loaden withal, (by men under whoſe tongues is the poyſon of Aſps) are Employments every way becoming thoſe who are Diſciples of the</hi> HOLY JESUS, <hi>and have ſolemnly promiſed to follow His Example, and which I am certain will ſpeak Peace and Comfort to them, when others who give themſelves the liberty to detract and defame, to ſcandalize and ill-report the Beſt of Men, will ſink at laſt under the Load of their own Guilt, and the Terrours of their angry and diſcontented Minds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſenſe of which has been a very great ſupport to my ſelf, ever ſince I have undertaken the Vindication of the Name and Memory of King</hi> CHARLES I. <hi>and has enabled me in ſome good ſort, to ſcorn and live above all thoſe Reproaches, that by a certain
<pb facs="tcp:62608:3"/>Faction, have been without Truth or Modeſty ſo freely faſtned upon me, and I am ſo far from being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Task I have engaged in, that I thank God, every freſh Provocation gives me the Pleaſure, as well as Advantage of knowing and underſtanding the incomparable Merits of that Great Man better, and the Courage to communicate them to others: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many other things that have come to my hand, ſince I began the Defence of this Great PRINCE, This, for the ſake of which I make bold to give Your Ladyſhip this Trouble at preſent, is one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and fulleſt that I ever ſaw, and no doubt will be ſatisfactory to all ſorts of Men, becauſe of the Perſon who was the Author of it; Namely, The chief Perſon of the</hi> Presbyterian Party <hi>in</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and the moſt employed by them for ſetting up and Vindicating their Kirk-Diſcipline. I have ſhewn it, ſince I had it, to ſeveral Perſons of great Names, and at great Poſts in our Church, who were all, as mightily taken with it, ſo deſirous it ſhould be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, that the World might ſee how unjustly this Great Perſons Name is dealt withal, by too great a Number of many Bad Men of this Age; which, as ſoon as I reſolved to Reprint, I at the ſame time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, it ſhould, with Your Ladyſhips Leave, come out under Your Honours Umbrage and Protection, which You have a Right to, not onely upon the ſcore
<pb facs="tcp:62608:3"/>of Your own Zeal for that Great Prince</hi>'s <hi>Memory and Vertues, but alſo upon the Account of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Integrity, the Loyalty and Steadineſs of Your Anceſtors to the CROWN and Dignity thereof; for it is well known, That Your Noble Grandfather loſt his Life, as General of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Forces at the firſt Fight againſt the Rebels at</hi> Edgelvill, <hi>for his Great Maſter's Just and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſe, and that Your as Noble Father, was at the ſame time impriſon'd, for his ſteady Adherence to the Royal Intereſt, and that both of them, as they ventured their Lives, ſo they greatly impaired a vaſt Eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But however that in the mean time, they Acted becoming Good Men, Good Chriſtians, and True Lavers of the Religion and Laws of their Country, which includes their being Good Subjects, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently took the better and more Juſtifiable Part; this enſuing Narrative, I am ſure, will make good and clear, to all Men who are not reſolved (let what will be ſaid) to continue their baſe and ill deſigned Prejudices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Declaration is this.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <head>
                           <hi>The Character of King</hi> CHARLES I.</head>
                        <p>VVHereas the greateſt part of the diſtempered Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theſe miſerable diſtracted Kingdoms, have been and are; wofully abuſed and miſled with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
<pb facs="tcp:62608:4"/>miſinformations againſt his ſacred Majeſty, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in point of Religion and moral-Wiſdom; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I confeſs with great grief of heart, my ſelf to have been (amongſt many moe of my coat) none of the leaſt; who out of Imaginary fears and jealouſies, were made real Inſtruments to advance this un-natural War, wherein ſo much Innocent Proteſtant Blood hath been ſhed, and ſo much downright Robbery committed, without fear, or ſhame of ſin; to the ſcandal of the true Reformed Religion, as cannot but draw down hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Judgements from Heaven upon theſe infatuated Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and more particularly upon Us who ſhould have inſtructed them in the way of Truth, Peace, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                        <p>I conceived it the duty of a good Chriſtian, eſpecially one of my profeſſion, and in the condition that I lie, expecting God Almighty's Call, not only to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the All-merciful God, with a humble ſincere remorſe of Conſcience, the greatneſs of this offence; which being done in ſimplicity of Spirit, I hope with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to obtain Mercy, becauſe I did it through Ignorance: But alſo, for the better ſatisfaction of all others, to publiſh this <hi>Declaration</hi> to the view of the World; to the intent, that all thoſe (eſpecially of the Miniſtery) who have been deluded with me, may by God's Grace, and my example (though a weak and mean Inſtrument) not only be undeceived themſelves, but alſo ſtirred up to undeceive others, with more ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie and facilitie; that the ſcandal may be removed from our Religion and Profeſſion, and the good King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his juſt Rights, and truly honoured and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as God's Anointed and Vicegerent upon Earth; and the poor diſtreſſed Subjects freed from thoſe intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Burdens and Oppreſſions which they lye groaning
<pb facs="tcp:62608:4"/>under, piercing Heaven with their Tears and Cries; and a ſolid Peace ſettled both in Kirk and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, throughout all His Majeſties Dominions, to the Glory of God, and of our bleſſed Mediator and Saviour the Lord Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>I do therefore Declare before God and the World, That ſince I had the Honour and Happineſs to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and Confer with His Majeſty, with all ſort of freedom; eſpecially in Matters of Religion, whether in relation to the Kirk or State, (which like <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> Twins are lynked together) that I found him the moſt intelligent Man that ever I ſpoke with; as far beyond my Epreſſion, as Expectation, grounded upon the Information that was given me (before I knew him) by ſuch as I thought ſhould have known him. I profeſs that I was oft-times aſtoniſh'd with the ſolidity and quickneſs of his Reaſons and Replies; wondred how he, ſpending his Time ſo much in Sports and Recreations, could have attained to ſo great Knowledge, and muſt confeſs ingenuouſly, that I was convinc'd in Conſcience, and knew not how to give him any reaſonable Satisfaction; yet, the ſweetneſs of his Diſpoſition is ſuch, that whatſoever I ſaid was well taken; I muſt ſay, that I never met with any Diſputant (let be a King, and in Matters of ſo high Concernment) of that mild and calm Temper, which convinced me the more, and made me think that ſuch Wiſdom and Moderation, could not be without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meaſure of divine grace: I had heard much of his carriage towards the Prieſts in <hi>Spain,</hi> and that King <hi>James</hi> told the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> upon his going thither, that he durſt venture his Son <hi>Charles</hi> with all the Jeſuits in the World, he knew him to be ſo well grounded in the Proteſtant Religion, but could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believe it before.</p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:62608:5"/>
                        <p> I obſerved all his actions, more particularly thoſe of devotion, which I muſt truly ſay, are more than ordinary; I informed my ſelf of others who had ſerved him from his Infancy, and they all aſſured me that there was nothing new or much enlarged in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his troubles, either in his private, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique way of exerciſe; twice a day conſtantly, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening for an hours ſpace in private; twice a day before dinner and ſupper in publick, beſides preachings upon Sundays, Tueſdays, and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary times; and no buſineſs though never ſo weighty and urgent can make him forget, or neglect this his tribute and duty to Almighty God. O that thoſe who ſit now at the helm of theſe weather bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Kingdoms had but one half of his true piety and wiſdom I dare ſay that the poor oppreſſed Subject ſhould not be plunged into ſo deep Gulfs of impiety, and miſery without compaſſion or pity; I dare ſay, if his advice had been followed, all the blood that is ſhed, and all the repair that is committed, ſhould have been prevented.</p>
                        <p>If I ſhould ſpeak of his Juſtice, Magnanimity, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Sobriety, Chaſtity, Patience; Humility, and of all his both Chriſtian and Moral Vertues, I ſhould run my ſelf into a Panegy rick, and ſeem to flatter him to ſuch as do not know him, if the preſent condition that I lye in did not exeem me from any ſuch ſuſpition of worldly ends, when I expect every hour to be called from all tranſitory vanities to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Felicity; and the diſcharging of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before God and men; did not oblige me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth ſimply and nakedly, in ſatisfaction of that which I have done ignorantly, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together innocently.</p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:62608:5"/>
                        <p> If I ſhould relate what I have received from good hands, and partly can witneſs of my own knowledge ſince theſe unhappy troubles began, I ſhould inlarge my ſelf into a Hiſtory: Let theſe brief Characters ſuffice. No man can ſay, that there is conſpicuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any predominant vice in him, a rare thing in a Man, but far rarer in a King: Never man ſaw him paſſionately angry, or extraordinarily moved, either with proſperity, or adverſity, having had as great Tryals as ever any King had: Never man heard him curſe, or given to ſwearing; Never man heard him complain, or bemoan his condiction, in the greateſt durance of War and confinement; When he was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from his deareſt Conſort, and deprived of the comfort of his Innocent Children, the hopefulleſt Princes that ever were in theſe ingrate Kingdoms; when he was denuded of this Counſellors and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Servants; No man can complain of the Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Wife or Daughters, though he hath had too many temptations in the prime of his age, by the inforced abſence of his Wife, which would be hardly taken by the meaneſt of his Subjects: and (which is beyond all admiration) being ſtript of all counſel and help of man, and uſed ſo harſhly as would have ſtupified any other man, then did his undaunted courage, and tranſcendent Wiſdom ſhew it ſelf more clearly, and vindicate him from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy of former times, to the aſtoniſhment of his greateſt Enemies: I confeſs this did ſo take me, that I could not but ſee the hand of God in it, and which will render His name glorious, and (I greatly fear) ours ignominious to all poſterity; he ſtands faſt to his grounds, and doth not riſe and fall with ſucceſs, the brittle ſquare of humane actions, and is ever rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:62608:6"/>to forgive all by-paſt injuries to ſettle a preſent ſolid Peace, and future tranquility, for the good of his Subjects; nay, for their cauſe he is content to forgoe ſo many of his own known, <hi>undoubted Juſt Rights;</hi> as <hi>may ſtand with their ſafety</hi> as <hi>Salus populi eſt Spurema Lex,</hi> ſo, <hi>&amp; ſi parendum eſt patri in eo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men non parendum quo efficitur ut non ſit Pater. [Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.]</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I confeſs that I could have wiſhed an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Presbyterial Government, in the Kirke of <hi>England,</hi> for the better Union between them and us, but I find the conſtitution of that Kingdom, and diſpoſition of that Nation ſo generally oppoſite, that it is not to be expected: They are a people natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined to freedom, and ſo bred in Riches and Plenty, that they can hardly be induced to embrace any Diſcipline that may any ways abridge their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Pleaſures. That which we eſteem a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kirk policy, inſtituted by the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles, is no better to them than a kind of ſlavery, and ſome do not ſtick to call it worſe than the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Inquiſition: Nay, even the greateſt part of thoſe who invited us to aſſiſt them in it, and ſent hither their Commiſſioners to induce us to enter into a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn national covenant for that effect, having ſerved their turn of us, to throw down the King and the Prelatical Party, and to poſſeſs themſelves with the ſupreame Government both of Kirke and State; are now Inventing evaſions to be rid of us, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude it, ſome of them publiſhing openly, in Pulpits and Print: That the ſacred Covenant was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the godly, but only as a trap to enſnare the Malignants, which cannot but bring heavy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from Heaven, and I am afraid, make a greater
<pb facs="tcp:62608:6"/>diſ-union between theſe Nations, than ever was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Like unto that <hi>bellum Gallicum, quod ſexcentis foederibus compoſitum, ſemper renovabatur</hi> [<hi>Canon. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Chron in here.</hi> 5. <hi>an. dom.</hi> 1118.] with a deluge of Chriſtian blood, and almoſt ruine of both Parties; or like unto that <hi>bellum Ruſticanum in Germania, in quo ſupra centena millia Raſticorum occubuerunt.</hi> [<hi>idem an. dom.</hi> 1524.] Or moſt of all, both in manner and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, reſembling that of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leydon, Munſer</hi> and <hi>Knoperduling,</hi> [<hi>idem an.</hi> 1534.] which took its riſe from the former; ſo many different Sects ſpring up daily more and more amongſt them, which all like <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes, Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> conſpire againſt the Lord's-Anoynted, and the true Proteſtant Religion.</p>
                        <p>The City of <hi>London</hi> that was ſo forward in the beginning of this glorious Reformation, ſurpaſſes now <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in number of Sects, and may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to old <hi>Rome, quae cum omnibus pene gentibus dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maretur omnium gentium erroribus ſerviebat, &amp; magnam ſibi videbatur aſſumpſiſſe Religionem quia nullam reſpue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat falſitatem. [Leo in Serm. de Petro &amp; Paulo. app.]</hi> their tranſgreſſions are like to bring them to that confuſion of the Iſraelites when they had no King, [<hi>Judg.</hi> 21.] every one did what ſeemed good in his own eyes, becauſe they feared not the Lord; [<hi>Jhoſ.</hi> 10.] they ſaid, What ſhould a King do to us? The young men preſumed to be wiſer than the elder, [<hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.] the viler ſort deſpiſed the honourable, <hi>[Lament, ult.]</hi> and the very ſerving men ruled over them.</p>
                        <p>I profeſs, when I ſaw theſe things ſo clearly, I could not blame the King to be ſo backward in giving his aſſent to the ſettling of our Presbyterial diſcipline in
<pb facs="tcp:62608:7"/>that Kirke, for the great inconveniences that might follow thereupon, to Him and his Poſterity, there being ſo many ſtrong Corporations in that Kingdom to lead on a Popular government, ſuch a number of people that have either no, or broken eſtates, who are ready to drive on any alteration, and ſo weak and powerleſs a Nobility to hinder it. <hi>Multos dulcedo proedarum, plures Res anguſtoe veb ambiguoe domi alios ſcelerum Conſcientia ſtimulabat. [C. Tacit.]</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, Madam, I hope thoſe Men, who have, of late, ſo boldly ventured to throw the moſt Stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Dirt in the Face of this Great Prince, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Martyr, will, by Repentance, give glory to God, and do ſo no more; in hopes of which, I, after my Prayers, and Earneſt Wiſhes, for the Preſervation of your Ladyſhip, and whole Family, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the long life, and health, of your Noble Lord; to whoſe good Counſels, and indefatigable Labours we of the Church of</hi> England <hi>owe ſo much, do take leave of your Ladyſhip, and ſubſcribe my ſelf,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladyſhip moſt Humble and Faithful Servant, <hi>Richard Hollingworth.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62608:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Further Defence</hi> OF THE KINGS Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reader;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THis Declaration of Mr. <hi>Henderſon</hi>'s was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to me ſome Weeks ago by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Lamplugh,</hi> Son to the late Arch-biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and it had been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed before now, but that I underſtood there was an Anſwer coming out againſt my Second Defence of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and therefore I was reſolved to ſtay a little longer, that ſo if there was any thing in it worth Anſwering, I might make but one Trouble of it; and at laſt out it came, with a Title as falſe as the greateſt part of the Book it ſelf; Namely, <hi>Ludlow no Lyar,</hi> which I do not doubt, but thou wilt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of, by that time thou haſt read a little further. The Truth of it is, the whole Book is ſo full of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and Malice, of Unmannerlineſs and Railing, of bald and falſe Aſſertions, of Slander and baſe Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that it is a Shame to, and a Confutation of it ſelf, and every Leaf of it ſtinks in the Noſtrils of all the good and ſober, of all the wiſe and unprejudic'd Readers, that I have either met with or can hear of; and it is a Diſhonour to the Cauſe of the Enemies of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. to have no better a Champion to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62608:8"/>throw down the Gauntlet in its behalf, and there are no men about the City cry it up, but the great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Monarchy and Epiſcopacy, let their Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Profeſſions be what they will.</p>
                  <p>The Book is Dedicated to a Reverend Kinſman of mine, under the Name of <hi>Wilſon</hi> from <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and what can we expect but Falſehood, when he begins at this rate? For my Kinſman aſſures me, there is no man of that Name in <hi>Yarmouth</hi> but an ordinary Saylor, and I hope the World will believe the Talent of ſuch a Man lyes otherwaies, than to write ſuch Letters: The ſhort is, the whole Book, as appears by the Stile, the Air and Scurrility of it all, is writ by one and the ſame Pen, and as ſo I ſhall Anſwer him.</p>
                  <p>The Party now ſo hotly engaged againſt Monarchy and Epiſcopacy, which they ſtrike at thro' the ſides of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. I know are very much enraged at my Defence of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Holy and Divine Book, and therefore take all Courſes to buoy up Dr. <hi>Walkers</hi> Credit, and to leſſen, or elſe to attempt to prove falſe the Authorities I have named, and to how good purpoſes this Anſwerer has done it, I now come to ſhew.</p>
                  <p>I tell the World <hi>pag.</hi> 7. of my Defence, the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe betwixt Sir <hi>John Brattle</hi> and my ſelf about that Book, and that he aſſur'd me that he helped his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in 47, to Methodize the Papers, that ſo far as they were then drawn up by the King, that made up the greateſt part of that Book, all writ with the Kings own hand; and I alſo aſſert, That Sir <hi>John</hi> has own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame ſince, not only to my ſelf, but many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my Friends. To which he Replies, That Sir <hi>John</hi> who he agrees with me, is a very worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62608:8"/>never told me nor any other Perſon, that the Papers he ſpoke of were writ with the King's own hand; and though the ſtreſs of the Evidence does not lye in that, for if they were writ in 47, Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Claim is out of doors; for Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> acknowledges they were not ſent to the King till the Treaty in 48, and that Treaty too, upon which the Troubles came ſo faſt upon the King, which was about a year after; yet for all that I do venture to tell him, that what he aſſerts of Sir <hi>John Brattle</hi> is falſe, and Sir <hi>John</hi> ſent me word that he was a Damnable Lyar, and is pleas'd with great Reſentment and Indignation, to declare he never told any man any ſuch thing, and that what he told me and my Friends as to the Kings hand is all true, and therefore he muſt be a Knight of the Poſt, that will venture to give his Oath for ſuch a thing; which indeed I ſhall not wonder at, conſidering what ſort of Men there are in the world, and what deſigns are carrying on by that ſort of Men at this time.</p>
                  <p>The next thing I aſſert is the Account of Mrs. <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi> whom he owns to appear a good and diſcreet Woman, and in earneſt, he ſaies he is aſſured her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Husband was ſo too, which I am glad to hear from him, for then I am ſure he would not dye with a Lye in his mouth, and if he did not, I know what Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> did.</p>
                  <p>I ſay Mrs. <hi>Simmonds</hi> told me her Husband declared to the laſt, the Book to be the Kings, Did ſhe deny this to his Friend that waited upon her? Not a word of it in his Letter, only I concealed the whole Truth, becauſe I did not ſay he dyed of the Small-Pox, which I never asked her, nor ſhe never told me, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did or no, it was not material to my buſineſs in hand, nor caſts any Reflection upon what I ſay,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62608:9"/>unleſs a Man cannot confeſs a Truth when he lies a dying of the Small-Pox, <hi>Riſum teneatis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I, but Mrs. <hi>Simmonds</hi> ſays, ſhe never heard of her Husbands being in a Shepherds Habit, and therefore Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Evidence is quite ruin'd certainly; now Reader take Notice, This is but a Circumſtance in Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Account, and no doubt is true, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Mrs. <hi>Simmonds</hi> Ignorance of it, for we all know all Men do not think fit in Undertakings of ſuch danger and difficulties, as this was of Printing and Correcting a Book of this nature, to make their Wives acquainted with every thing they do in order to ſave themſelves; but what is this to Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? As to Mr. <hi>Odert</hi>'s Tranſcribing of it, and they printing it by his Copy and no other, which as Mr. <hi>Milbourn</hi> the Printer has ſince aſſured me, came all at once to them, which wholly ſpoyls that Aſſertion of Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s, of bringing ſome of the laſt ſheets to the Preſs by Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Order. Further, What is this to Dr. <hi>Jerem. Tayler</hi>'s getting leave by Letter of the King, to change the Title from the <hi>Royal Plea,</hi> (with which they printed the firſt ſheet) into <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>? For the Reaſons Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi> in this Narrative aſſerts, which wholly routs Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Excuſe to Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> when he thought he could not with a good Conſcience write ſuch a Book in the KING's Name; and he Anſwered, <hi>Look upon the Title, who draws his own Picture:</hi> Theſe Accounts of Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi> ought to have been diſproved by this Anſwerer, or elſe the Evidence is as clear as the Sun at Noon, and ſo I do not doubt will continue, notwithſtanding all this fooliſh barking at it; but it is common, when Men want Reaſon, they fall to little and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cavils, as our Author has here done.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62608:9"/>
                  <p> Another thing I name for the weaking Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>'s Aſſertion, that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> was the Author of that Excellent Book of the King's, is what paſſed betwixt Dr. <hi>Meriton,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> at the late Lord Mayors Sir <hi>Tho. Pilkington</hi>'s: I ſay Dr. <hi>Meriton</hi> told me that he put Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> to ſilence, with the Story of Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> lending Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> the Book, and Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s tranſcribing it, and ſo returning it to Mr. <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> again, and that Mr. <hi>Marryot</hi> ſtood by, heard the debate, and did juſtifie Dr. <hi>Meriton</hi>'s Conqueſt of Dr. <hi>Walker.</hi> And what ſays my Adverſary to this? Why here he claps his Wings and Crows, and ſays, I have committed two Miſtakes, that the Diſcourſe was not at dinner but after dinner, and that Dr. <hi>Meriton</hi> began the diſcourſe with Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> and not Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> with Dr. <hi>Meriton,</hi> and by theſe two things he vainly fancies he has invalidated the whole Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: Now ſuppoſe I did miſtake as to theſe two petty Circumſtances, which I am pretty well aſſur'd I did not, for Dr. <hi>Meriton</hi> told the ſtory as occaſioned by meeting together at my Lord Mayors dinner, and did not as far as I can remember deſcend to ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute particulars. Pray good Reader, What is this to the ſtory it ſelf; namely, The affirming he did ſo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> that he had not a Word to ſay for himſelf? Which is ſo true, and will be upon juſt occaſion atteſted by others as well as my ſelf, that I do here in the face of the World, challenge Dr. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riton,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Marryot,</hi> to deny one ſyllable of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, either as to the one his telling his ſucceſs in the diſpute, and the other juſtifying of it as really true.</p>
                  <p>The next thing I produce againſt Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> is Mr. <hi>Long</hi>'s Evidence, and his atteſting in two Letters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62608:10"/>to Dr. <hi>Goodall,</hi> that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> did affirm to him, that he was fully convinced that the Book was entirely the King's own Work, and what ſays my Anſwerer to this ſtabbing Evidence? For for truly it is, and I am ſure gives the Faction a great deal of Vexation and foaming Rage; why truly the Reply to this is very diverting, Mr. <hi>Long</hi> writ the <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Long</hi> is againſt Free Prayer and Comprehenſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what then, is Mr. <hi>Long</hi> not to be believ'd becauſe of his Opinion as to theſe things? Has Mr. <hi>Long</hi> by any art of Immorality, Sedition or Rebellion, wholly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his Credit or Reputation, ſo that his Word is not to be taken? No Reader, upon a juſt Enquiry, I find him to be a grave, learned, ſerious, and pious Divine, in that eſteem amongſt his Brethren, that I will venture again to ſay, That it is no diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Dr. <hi>walker</hi>'s Memory, to aſſert, that his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is to be heeded and believed before Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>'s, and I am not willing to be provoked (becauſe the one of them is dead) to give my Reaſons for it.</p>
                  <p>There are two things more I give the World an Account of in my Defence of this Great Mans being the Author of that Book, which were too hot for my Adverſaries fingers, and therefore he durſt not touch them; The one is Major <hi>Huntington</hi>'s Story, told from his own mouth by a Non-conformiſt-Miniſter to my ſelf; Namely, That ſome of thoſe Papers, that were part of that Book, were taken at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> kept by General <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and obtained from him by the Major, and afterwards by him preſented to the King, and here I challenge him or any Man, to deny the Truth of this Story, and that becauſe that Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt-Miniſter is of ſuch eſteem and credit in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that I am ſure they will bluſh to deny what he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62608:10"/>aſſerts, if I ſhould name him, which I am ready to do when called by Authority.</p>
                  <p>The other Story is about Dr. <hi>Dillingham</hi>'s aſſerting, That he ſaw and read part of this Book of the King's, and that long before Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> pretended to ſend it to the King. Now know Reader, that this Account was given me by a Reverend and Learned Miniſter in <hi>London,</hi> as well as he could remember it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we might have a more full and ſatisfactory Relation of it, I got him to write to Dr. <hi>Dillingham</hi>'s Son a Miniſter, and to deſire him to let us know what Communications his Father had made to him about this Matter, who civilly returned this enſuing Anſwer, which I am ſure will not be unpleaſing to all thoſe who are Friends to Truth and Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Have heard of that Controverſie you mention, and have now in my hands Dr.</hi> Hollingworth's <hi>Book, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is ſomething ſaid concerning my Fathers bearing Witneſs to the Truth of King</hi> Charles <hi>being the Author of <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, though there might be ſomething added to that Relation as to the time and place when and where he was a Eye-witneſs of it: An Account whereof, as near as I can remember, from what I have had from his own mouth, is as follows. While the King was at</hi> Holmeby <hi>my Father went from</hi> Cambridge <hi>to wait upon this Earl of</hi> Montague's <hi>Father, who was then with the King there; while the King was at Dinner, one of the Bed-Chamber ſhewed my Father the King's Cloſet, wherein was his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary and Papers, while he was there, he that came with him was accidentally called away, when my Father ſeeing a Black Box on the Table, that was lock'd but not very cloſe, ſpyed a corner of a Paper hanging out, and took the boldneſs to draw it ſo far out, as that he could read ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62608:11"/>Sentences; it was newly written in a fair hand, which he judged to be the King's own, and he told me when he real the King's Book in print, he found in one Chapter the very ſame things word for word (as far as he could remember) with that Manuſcript Paper. What Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King was then writing of I cannot tell, neither did I ever ask my Father, but if I may conjecture of it at this distance, I ſhould gueſs it might be that wherein he Complains of being deprived of his Chaplains; for while my Father was there, the Parliament ſent down ſome Chaplains of their own to attend upon Him. Thus Sir you have what I can recollect concerning this Matter: Be pleas'd, not only in this, but in whatſoever elſe I can ſerve you, to Command.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your ready Servant and Faithful Friend, <hi>Tho, Dillingham.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>A little before this Letter came to my hands, I had another from a Learned Fellow of <hi>Trinity College</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> with an encloſed Paper in it, taken by his own hands from the Original, now in the poſſeſſion of the Gentlemans own Son, Fellow of <hi>Exeter College,</hi> which encloſed was this:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF</hi> any one has a deſire to know the True Author of a Book Entituled <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I, one of the Servants of King <hi>Charles I.</hi> in his Bed-Chamber, do declare, when his ſaid Majeſty was Priſoner in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> That I read over the above-mentioned Book (which was long before the ſaid Book was printed) in his Bed-Chamber writ with his Majesties own hand, with ſeveral Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linings. Moreover his Majeſty King <hi>Charles I.</hi> told me,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62608:11"/>
                     <hi>Sure</hi> Levet, <hi>you do deſign to get this Book by heart,</hi> having often ſeen me reading of it. I can Teſtifie alſo, That <hi>Royſton</hi> the Printer told me, that he was impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd by <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> the Protector, becauſe he would not declare that King <hi>Charles I.</hi> was not the Author of the ſaid Book.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Signed and Sealed <date>
                           <hi>Octob. 16th 1690.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <lb/>
                     <signed>Wil. Levet.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And again underſtanding that one Mr. <hi>Hearne</hi> now Schoolmaſter of <hi>Amesbury,</hi> and formerly <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> to Sr. <hi>Phillip Warwick,</hi> who waited upon the King at the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> as a Clark and Writer, as did alſo Mr. <hi>Odert</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> could give me ſome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from Sr. <hi>Phillip</hi> as to this Book; I went to him when he was laſt in <hi>London,</hi> and deſired to know what Aſſiſtance he could give me, as to the proving the Truth of the Books being the Kings, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with his own hand gave me this following Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I Robert Hearne,</hi> formerly Servant to Sir <hi>Phillip Warwick,</hi> do Atteſt, That I have often heard my ſaid Maſter Sir <hi>Phil. Warwick,</hi> as likewiſe Mr. <hi>Odert</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> declare, That they had Tranſcribed Copies of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt's</hi> own Copy of his Book Entituled <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> written with His ſaid Majeſties own hand.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Witneſs my hand,<lb/> 
                              <hi>In the Preſence of,</hi>
                              <lb/> Phil. Miſt,<lb/> Fr. Shipton.</dateline>
                           <signed>Robert Hearne.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I have but one thing more to take notice of as to this Matter, and that is a Story of this Authors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62608:12"/>Mrs. <hi>Gaudens</hi> declaring to Biſh. <hi>Nicholſon</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> upon receiving the Sacrament, that her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band wrote the Book, how far this man is to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, as to any Story he tells, I leave the Reader, who has looked his Book over impartially, to judge; but however, ſeeing he is ſo fond of, and ſo apt to pick up any thing that he thinks will ſerve his wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, even to the very Miſtakes of the Preſs, as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in the Words <hi>Barking</hi> and <hi>Recalled,</hi> with which he makes ſuch ridiculous Work; I will give him a <hi>Rowland</hi> for his <hi>Oliver,</hi> and will Anſwer this Story with another quite contrary to his, from the ſame Gentlewoman; There is a Reverend and Learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter now of <hi>London,</hi> who does aſſure me, that a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of good Quality told him ſixteen Years agoe, That being in diſcourſe with Mrs. <hi>Gauden,</hi> ſhe told her that ſhe had a great Concern for the Eternal State of her Husband, becauſe he pretended to be the Author of that Book, when to her knowledge he never writ it; the Reverend Perſon tells me he has forgot the Ladies Name, or elſe he would freely have had his own men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, but the Story it ſelf he very well remembers, and I am ſure he is to be credited as much as any man that wears a Gown.</p>
            <p>And thus good Reader, thou haſt here Sir <hi>John Brat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>'s Teſtimony for the Book in 47, Mrs. <hi>Simmondſes,</hi> that her Husband dyed, aſſerting the Book to be the Kings own; Dr. <hi>Meriton</hi>'s declaring his putting Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> to ſilence, with his Story of Mr. <hi>Simmonds;</hi> Mr. <hi>Cliffords</hi> Account of Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> committing it to the Preſs by the King's Command, together with Alteration of the Title by Dr. <hi>Jerem. Tayler,</hi> and his Compoſing and Correcting it not from Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s, but Mr. <hi>Odert</hi>'s own Copy; Mr. <hi>Long</hi>'s Letters poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62608:12"/>declaring Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s confeſſing it to be the King's own Book, Major <hi>Huntington</hi> aſſuring a Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt Miniſter, that he preſented ſome of the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that made up part of the Book taken at <hi>Nazeby</hi> Fight, which was three years before Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> ſent it to the King; Dr. <hi>Dillingham</hi>'s reading ſome of the Book preſently after the King came from <hi>Newcastle;</hi> Mr. <hi>Levet</hi>'s ſeeing and reading the Book in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight</hi> a great while before it was printed, and Mr. <hi>Hearne</hi>'s Teſtimony from Sir <hi>Phil. Warwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Odert</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> who all attended the King in his Impriſonment as Clerks and Writers; and if all theſe will not weigh down the vain Tattle and confident Say-ſo of ſingle Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> from ſingle Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> then the Lord have Mercy upon us; for we muſt needs be got to an almoſt <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State of Incredulity; From which good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>Good Reader, there is one thing more to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, which had almoſt ſlipt my Memory, and that is this bold mans triumphing over King <hi>Charles</hi> I. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcore of a Prayer taken out of Sir <hi>Phillip Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi>'s <hi>Arcadia,</hi> made to an Heathen God; and as he impudently aſſert, made uſe of by him in the time of his Captivity. Now I muſt deſire thee to obſerve, the Spight as well as Falſity of this Reflection; for if Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> made this whole Book, as Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> aſſerts, and the Copy he ſent to the King was never returned, nor made uſe of in any of the Impreſſions, then the Prayer was put in by Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> and the King no ways concerned in it, and conſequently it is a Scandal founded in the greateſt Malice and ill Will to the Reputation and Vertue of this Great Man; but as I deny, and have fully proved that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62608:13"/>not the Author of this Book, ſo I muſt acquaint thee, that this Prayer, which this man makes himſelf and his Party ſo prophanely merry withal, was not prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the firſt Edition, by that Copy ſent by Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> to the Preſs, but was foiſted in afterwards by ſome crafty and deſigning Perſon, on purpoſe to expoſe the Book, and to leſſen that deſerved Credit and Influence that they found it had amongſt, and upon all the wiſe and conſidering men of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and therefore I expect to hear no more of this baſe Story for the time to come, or if they will take the boldneſs to raiſe it again, I hope Reader, I have furniſhed thee with a ſufficient Anſwer to it.</p>
            <div type="statement">
               <head>Some ſhort Remarks upon a Lewd Book, called, <hi>Ludlow no Lyar.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reader;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter a certain bold Libeller had ſent into the World a Second Arraignment of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>First,</hi> by way of Letter to my ſelf, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touch'd with the Sence of the ill Effects that Book might have upon the credulous and unthinking part of the Nation, did think it convenient to let the world know, the falſe Imputations he had laid at the King's door, and therefore in order to it, did conſult and make uſe of ſuch Authorities, as I thought unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, and I am ſure are for the moſt part ſo (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one) which I have been but lately Convinced of, and which is one of their own, and which they make no little uſe of; but let the Authorities be what they will, this Wicked Man is reſolved to be in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62608:13"/>right, as long as there is any rude Vote or ſcandalous Libel, Remonſtrance, or falſe Story to be found in print, and to be communicated to this preſent Age, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Friend nor Enemy, if they write any thing in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the great King ought to be believed, if he may have his Will, and let what Acts of Parliament be quoted for the Juſtification of that Prince, yet he ſtill was a Tyrant, and a Man neither of Honour nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: But to my main deſign, in which I promiſe to be very ſhort.</p>
               <p>Firſt Reader, I muſt deſire thee to take Notice, That I have Dedicated my Second Defence to the Arch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Nobility, Gentry, Clergy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Nation, in which I tell them of the Books that have been Printed ſince this laſt Revolution, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Conſtitution both of Church and State, which did ſufficiently ſhew the Deſign on Foot, to which not one Word of Anſwer is this Libel: I fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell them what Deſtruction this Spirit once back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with power will make of them and all they have, of which no Notice taken, for which indeed I do not blame him; for he knows in his Conſcience all I ſay is true, and I hope the Body of the Nation for the time to come, will be ſo wiſe and provident, as not to let things run ſo far, as to make a Second Tryal of that Spirit, by which they have ſuffered, and that ſo ſmartly already.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of my Defence, I do honeſtly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid him for taking upon him the Name of that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and tell him that he ought to ſuffer in his ſtead, being ſo forward to Repreſent him, and Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thoſe Actions for which he ſtands Condemned; and this he is pleaſed to paſs by too, no doubt being convinced if he had his due, he would quickly be put
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62608:14"/>out of Capacity of poyſoning the Nation with ſuch Infamous Pamphlets.</p>
               <p>The next thing I ſhall make a few Remarks upon, is the Letter of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> to the Pope; I tell him in my Defence, that as the Letter is in <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> his Accuſations of that Great Prince from that Letter, are falſe and made up of Lyes, upon which he grows great in his own eyes, and triumphs over me as if he had got a compleat Victory, leaving me dead upon the ſpot; for he produces another Letter, in which is contained all he Charges upon the Prince.</p>
               <p>The Truth is, I had heard a little before his Libel came out, from a Reverend Neighbour of mine, that Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> in his Firſt Edition Dedicated to <hi>Rich. Cromewel</hi> then called Protector, had put in this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his, but afterwards in thoſe Editions after the Reſtoration, not being able to juſtifie the Letter, put this in the room of it, both which I have good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe are alike true; that is, they are both of them ſpurious, and I Challenge this bold Writer, or any of his Party, to name a man that ever ſaw or took either of theſe Letters out of any Archive or Publick Record at <hi>Rome, Madrid,</hi> or <hi>London;</hi> that there was a Letter ſent to the Pope, I grant, but that it was pleaſing to the Pope, I deny, and that for this very Reaſon, becauſe the Pope did ſo greatly delay the Diſpenſation for the Marriage, which I dare ſay he would not have done if he had had ſuch hopes of making <hi>England</hi> Catholick, as they call it again, as ſuch a Letter as this from ſuch a Perſon that was next to the Crown, did give him. The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> knew <hi>England</hi> ſo well, and the Advantages of it to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Chair, that I am ſure he would have granted an hundred Diſpenſations at firſt asking, for ſuch an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62608:14"/>as this: But good Reader, I muſt entreat thee to obſerve, that this Libeller, though he makes ſuch a Noiſe about a Letter, which could not (all Circumſtances conſidered) be avoided, yet he takes no Notice of what I aſſert, as to the Princes anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Favourite, that he came for a Wife and not for a Religion, nor of Mr. <hi>Ruſhworths</hi> Atteſtation of his ſteadineſs to his Religion, nor of Mr. <hi>Johnſons</hi> Account, of his fixedneſs to his Principles, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Applications of the Prieſts to him; No, no, theſe things do not anſwer the ends of this man and his Party, which, in ſhort, are to deſtroy Church and State, and therefore not one Word of them, or any other Vertues of this Prince I will war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you; and therefore the Old Cry of one of his Judges, is ſtill among them, <hi>Blacken him, blacken him,</hi> as this man has done to purpoſe with his Lyes and falſe Accuſations.</p>
               <p>As for the Story of <hi>Prynne, Baſtwicke</hi> and <hi>Burton,</hi> with whoſe Sufferings he endeavours to beſpatter the Reign and Spirit of King <hi>Charles I.</hi> I will onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him over and above what I ſaid in my Anſwer to his lewd Libel, with this true Account, which I promiſe to make good when ever called to it by my Superiours; Namely, That Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> being in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with a Friend of mine, after the Happy Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, told him to this purpoſe, That the Crimes of himſelf and his Fellow Sufferers were ſo great, that if the Juſtice of the Nation had cut off their Heads inſtead of their Ears, they had had nothing but what was due to them; by which Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> who knew his and their Deſerts better than this Defender of them, either does or will, ſhewed himſelf a true Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and one that would have ſcorned as well as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62608:15"/>grieved for ſuch an Advocate, as this wicked man is.</p>
               <p>The next thing he falls foul upon me, is for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing favourably of Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> whom he treats with all the ſcurrility imaginable; now I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, though I believe that great and learned Man was miſtaken in the temper of the Nation, and did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things with too great an Heat and Zeal, yet upon reading his Story, I do believe, that as he was a great Scholar, ſo he was a very pious Man, and a thouſand times more abus'd by a Generation of men, than he did deſerve, he lived ſtrictly, and dyed with a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Comfort, and Satisfaction of Mind ſuitable to his holy and ſevere Life; and for the Proof of this I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee, Reader, to read over his Speech he made in defence of himſelf, upon his Tryal, before the few Lords that took upon them to be his Judges, and that holy Diſcourſe he made upon the Scaffold, juſt before that fatal Blow that ſevered his Head from his Body.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſtands in his Aſſertion, That Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> ſent the Common-Prayer-Book to the Pope and Cardinals for their Approbation, and quotes one <hi>Gage</hi> a Fryar for the Truth of it, I muſt beg thy leave, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to tell thee that I do not believe the Story, and that becauſe ſuch a man as <hi>Gage</hi> reports it, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that time when Uſurpers were in the Chair, and with whom, as other Popiſh Converts were wont to do, he was reſolved to curry favour, and I believe this man the leſs, becauſe he was ſo ſilly and ſo ſpiteful, as to vindicate Biſhop <hi>Lauds</hi> Death as juſt, when he could not but know, if he underſtood any thing of our Legal Conſtitution, that Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was cut off by a Warrant that no Law of <hi>England</hi> juſtifies; for it was done without the Kings Conſent or Hand, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in plain terms, that he was murder'd, and he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62608:15"/>that Vindicates the Breach of the Sixth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Teſtimony ſhall have no Credit with me, nor will, I am ſure, with any good and undeſigning man throughout the Kingdom. Another thing I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his former vile Paper withal, is what is ſaid by Mr. <hi>Whitelock,</hi> concerning the <hi>Scotch</hi> Rebellion, who tells us, (though a Friend to the Party) what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions the King made, how He kept his Word, and the Rebels broke theirs, after a ſolemn Agreement betwixt them both, who tells us of their Signing a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>French</hi> King to come in to their Aid againſt their lawful Soveraign, And what ſays my Adverſary to theſe things? Why he quotes ſeveral Defences they made, nothing to the purpoſe as to what Mr. <hi>Whitelock</hi> aſſerts, and indeed ſuch things as any Rebels may ſay for themſelves, and he knows there never yet was ſo bad a Cauſe, but Wit and Malice could invent and draw up ſomething that dazzled the eyes of the Vulgar, and ſerved to keep ignorant, or deſigning men in a Body together: But good Reader, I pray take Notice, That whereas I give an Account from Mr. <hi>Whitelock,</hi> how far Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> intereſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this Rebellion of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and how he ſent <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> his Chaplain, and <hi>Hepburn</hi> his Page, to blow up the Coals both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Puritans,</hi> yet my Adverſary is pleaſed here to be utterly ſilent and to paſs it by, no doubt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſo notorious and villainous a Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as would admit of no manner of Juſtification.</p>
               <p>The next thing I Advocate for this Great King for, are his many and gracious Favours and Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in paſſing ſo many Bills for the firſt Year of the Parliaments ſitting down, which he would make the World believe, were no Favours, but what he was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62608:16"/>bound to do, and conſequently, for which, no Thanks were due to him, by which he takes off all Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Their Preſent Majeſties and their Succeſſors from the People, as to any future Acts of Grace they grant, for which I am ſure he deſerve no Thanks from the Crown, and indeed for which he ought to be look'd upon as a downright Enemy to the future Intercourſe and good Underſtanding betwixt Their Majeſties and their People, and I doubt not but this ſaucy Aſſertion will be ſo thought of both by King and People, and the Loyalty of him and his pretending Party will be looked upon accordingly.</p>
               <p>I further in my Defence, vindicate the King's Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſcience, as to the Execution of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and to ſhew the reaſonableneſs of the Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (which he baſely makes ſport withal) recite and print the Preamble of the Act of Parliament, by which the Attainder of that Great Man, and White Soul, as Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> who attended him upon the Scaffold, calls him, was taken off, in which they acquit him of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, And what ſays this Pamphleteer to this? Not a Word, but according to his uſual Modeſty calls him Traytor; and conſequently Arraigns the Wiſdom and Juſtice of the Nation, which indeed to me is no wonder, conſidering the Venemous Spirit of the man throughout his whole Book.</p>
               <p>Further I Vindicate the King, and that from his own Declaration (which I have printed in words at length) from any deſign of bringing up the Army to plunder the City of <hi>London,</hi> which Declaration he ſays little or nothing to, but flies preſently to a Committee, and their Examinations of the thing, which truly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how at that time ſome men were allured with hopes, others affrighted with Frown and Threats, I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62608:16"/>can give but little heed to, and I will be ſo hardy as to tell the World, that I will believe the Aſſertions of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. before Twenty Committees of thoſe days, conſidering the deſigns then on foot, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to carry them on; and I muſt confeſs, ever ſince I read <hi>Whites</hi> Centuries, the Witneſſes received, and the ruine of ſo many Families upon ſuch Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, I have had but a very ſlender Value for what was printed from thoſe Committees; let this man an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer what the King ſays upon this Account in his own Defence, and what the Officers of the Army ſay in their Petition in their behalf, and then he will act like a clear Anſwerer, and deſerve a further Conſideration.</p>
               <p>Another thing I Charge this modeſt and mannerly Gentleman withal, is his falſe Account he gives in his former Libel of the Rabble running down to <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in a riotous and tumultuous manner, who he ſays went only armed with Petitions in their hands in a peaceable way, as to which I tell him, and that truly, that he contradicts all the Hiſtorians of that Age, and that they were ſo far from ſuch a decent Carriage as he aſſerts, that they with Clubs and Staves in their hands, cryed out they would have no Groom-Porters-Lodge at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> but would ſpeak with the King himſelf when they pleaſed, that they beſet the Houſe of Lords door, and cryed <hi>Juſtice, Juſtice,</hi> that they broke the Organ, and tore the Veſtments of the Church of <hi>Westminſter</hi> in pieces, threw ſtones at the Biſhops, and endangered the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi>'s Life: And what ſays he to theſe things in his Reply? Why tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not one Word, but ſtill ſillily and againſt all Truth, would make the World believe the King was not at all affronted, and had no Reaſon to leave <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which he muſt be a great Stranger to Matters of Fact, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62608:17"/>gives any Credit to ſuch bold Aſſertions; and I am ſure this man, in this particular, if any man believe him, muſt be beholden to his blind Credulity, and not to his Skill in Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>Another thing I call this man to Account for, is his bold aſſerting the Kings burning by the Hang-man, his own Pacification with the <hi>Scots</hi> when he came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which I refute by a Paſſage out of Biſhop <hi>Burnets</hi> Memoirs of the two <hi>Hamiltons;</hi> it is true, the Figures are miſtaken, but the Story is truly, related as it is in that Biſhops Book, but to convince the World of the Malice, as well as Falſeneſs of this Reflection, I ſhall preſent them with a greater Authority than the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and that is an Act of State againſt the <hi>Scots</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a ſcandalous Paper diſperſed by them, which the Reader may find at large in the Council Table-Book.</p>
               <p>On Sunday the Fourth of <hi>August</hi> 1639. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty being in Council, was pleaſed to acquaint the Lords with a Paper he had ſeen at <hi>Barwicke,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Some Conditions of His Majeſties Treaty with his Subjects of</hi> Scotland, which Paper being in moſt parts full of falſhood, diſhonour and ſcandal, to His Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the late Pacification; All which Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, the whole Board unanimouſly became humble Petitioners to His Majeſty, that this falſe and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Paper might be burnt by the Hang-man, to which Petition the Earl of <hi>Pembrooke, Salisbury</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> afterward known Enemies to the King's Cauſe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. And now I hope this will ſtop this mans, and his Friends mouths as to this particular for the time to come, though conſidering the Malice of the man to the Memory of King <hi>Charles,</hi> I am apt to queſtion it.</p>
               <p>As to what he and I both ſay concerning the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62608:17"/>about the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, I ſhall paſs it by at preſent, and refer thee Reader, to the Vindication I make by two undoubted Papers of the King's Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as to that horrid Rebellion, at the latter end of this Paper.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing I aſſert in the behalf of this Great and Vertuous Prince, is what he ſays himſelf upon the Scaffold, as to the firſt beginning of that unhappy, and indeed needleſs War on the Parliaments ſide, where he Clears himſelf, by calling GOD to Witneſs, unto whom he was ſhortly to give an Account, that they began the War with him, for the Truth of which he refers to the Dates of both their Commiſſions, to which I have not one Word of Anſwer from this bold Libeller, but in a ſhuffling way talking of pawning Crown Jewels, which for what ends it was done, or deſigned to be done, it is not fit for him and I to judge, for the Actions of Princes are above our Reach, and ought not to be ſo narrowly pryed into, yet I dare ſay it was not to begin a War, becauſe the Good Man ſo often proteſts againſt any Intention of War, becauſe ſo ſmall a Sum of Money in compariſon, would ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle have anſwered an Undertaking againſt ſo great and powerful an Enemy, as the Parliament then was, and though the King afterwards made that uſe of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, after the War was actually commenced againſt him, yet that is no Argument, That that was the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Deſign.</p>
               <p>And now Reader, having given thee theſe ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon this filthy and ſcurrilous Book, I have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more to entertain thee withal, than to tell thee, That this Author, has with a great deal of Boldneſs and Falſhood, declared, notwithſtanding the honeſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I have given of my ſelf from the Age of <hi>Twenty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62608:18"/>One,</hi> and of my being Ordained by the hands of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> as ſoon as by Law I was capable, namely at the Age of <hi>Twenty Three,</hi> that I was a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian; but to Anſwer this in ſhort, I do here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in the Preſence of God, that I never was a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian in my Life, and further, by God's Grace, that I never will be one, for I neither like the Principles of that Government, nor the Spirit of too many of that Party, for I abhor all Bitterneſs and Cruelty.</p>
               <p>As for what he repeats out of <hi>Manvel,</hi> which were made againſt Dr. <hi>Parker,</hi> I pray God forgive him, it is a Deſcription that belongs not at all to me, as all thoſe know, who have been acquainted with the courſe of my Life, nor yet do Dr. <hi>Wildes</hi> Verſes againſt Dr. <hi>Lee</hi> reach me at all; for I bleſs God, ever ſince I came to a competent Underſtanding, I have loved the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and done what in me lay, to promote its true Intereſt, and which I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe to do, as long as I have Tongue to ſpeak, and a Pen to write.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this part of my Diſcourſe with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prayers to God for my Adverſary, that God would open his Eyes, and change his Heart before he dies, that ſo this Iniquity may not be for his Eternal Ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Iriſh Rebellion</hi> falſly and ſcandalouſly imputed to King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO make good which, I onely deſire thee Reader, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to peruſe the Two following Accounts: The one is a Letter by that Kings own Order, by the Hands of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Vane</hi> to the Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland, Borelaſe</hi> and <hi>Parſons,</hi> above half a year before the Rebellion, giving them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Intelligence the King had from abroad, of ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62608:18"/>Deſigns by the Popiſh Party againſt the Peace of that Kingdom, that ſo they might be awakened to take all poſſible care to prevent them: The other is an unfolding the whole Myſtery of the pretended Commiſſion with the King's Broad Seal to it, which the Enemies of that King have, and do ſtill charge that gracious Prince withal, and by Vertue of which they do lay all the innocent Blood then ſo barbarouſly ſpilt, at his door, and conſequently do endeavour thereby to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Name odious to all ſucceeding Generations, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is by Dr. <hi>Ker</hi> Dean of <hi>Ardagh,</hi> and as I am aſſured by a conſiderable Dignitary of that Kingdom, yet alive.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi>'s Letter to the Lords Juſtices concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Informations of Danger in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>HIS Majeſty hath Commanded me to acquaint your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips with an Advice given him from abroad, and confirm'd by his Miniſters in <hi>Spain</hi> and elſewhere, which in this Diſtemper'd Time, and Conjuncture of Affairs, deſerves to be ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, and an eſpecial care and watchfulneſs to be had therein: which is, That of late there have paſſed from <hi>Spain</hi> (and the like may well have been from other Parts) an unſpeakable number of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Church-men for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſome good old Souldiers under pretext of asking leave to raiſe Men for the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> whereas it is obſerved, among the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Friars there, a whiſper runs, as if they expected a Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in <hi>Connaght.</hi> Wherefore His Majeſty thought fit to give your Lordſhips this notice, that in your Wiſdoms, you might manage the ſame with that Dexterity and Secreſie, as to Diſcover and Prevent ſo pernicious a Deſign, if any ſuch there ſhould be, and to have a watchful Eye on the Proceedings and Actions of thoſe who come thither from abroad, on what pretext ſoever, and ſo herewith I reſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>White-Hall,</hi> 
                           <date>March <hi>the 16th 1640.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble Servant,</hi> Henry Vane.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <q>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62608:19"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <head>Dr. <hi>Ker</hi> Dean of <hi>Ardagh</hi> his Depoſition concerning the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny thrown upon King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, for giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Commiſſion to the Rebels in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I John Ker</hi> Dean of <hi>Ardagh,</hi> having occaſionally diſcourſed with the Right Honourable <hi>George</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Lanesborrough,</hi> concerning the late Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Lordſhip at that time having deſired to certifie the ſaid Diſcourſe under my Hand and Seal, do declare as followeth.</p>
                           <p>That I was preſent in Court when the Rebel Sir <hi>Phelim Oneal</hi> was brought to his Tryal in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and that he was Tryed in that Court which is now the High Court of Chancery, and that his Judges were Judge <hi>Donelan,</hi> afterwards Sir <hi>James Donelan,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Bolton</hi> Knight, ſometimes Lord Chief Baron of the <hi>Exchequer; Dungan,</hi> then called Judge <hi>Dungan,</hi> and another Judge whoſe name I do not now remember. And that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Witneſſes then brought in againſt him, there was one <hi>Joſeph Travers</hi> Clerk, and one Mr. <hi>Michael Harriſon,</hi> if I miſtake not his Chriſtian name; and that I heard ſeveral Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Murthers proved againſt him, the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> he having nothing material to plead in his own defence: And that the ſaid Judge, whoſe name I remember not as aboveſaid, Examined the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> about a Commiſſion, that the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> ſhould have had from <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> as the ſaid Judge then called the late King, for levying the ſaid War: That the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> made Anſwer, That he never had any ſuch Commiſſion; and that it was proved then in Court, by the Teſtimony of the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Travers</hi> and others; that the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> had ſuch a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and did in the beginning of the ſaid <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion ſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> the ſame unto the ſaid <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and ſeveral others then in Courts. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> confeſſed, that when he ſurpriſed the Caſtle of <hi>Charle-mount,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Caulfield,</hi> that he Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſaid Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> and another Gentleman, whoſe name I now do not remember, to cut off the King's broad Seal from a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the ſaid Lord's, they then found in <hi>Charle-mount,</hi> and to affix it to a Commiſſion, which he the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> had ordered to be drawn up. And that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> did in the face of the whole Court confeſs, that by the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi>'s order he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62608:19"/>did ſtitch the Silk Cord or Label of that Seal, with Silk of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the ſaid Label, and ſo fixed the Label and Seal to the ſaid Commiſſion, and that the ſaid Sir <hi>Edward Bolton,</hi> and Judge <hi>Donelan,</hi> urging the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> to declare why he did ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the People? He did Anſwer, That no Man could blame him, to uſe all means whatſoever to promote that Cauſe he had ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in. And that upon the ſecond day of his Tryal ſome of the ſaid Judges told him, that if he could produce any material proof, that he had ſuch a Commiſſion from the ſaid <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and prove it before Sentence ſhould paſs againſt him, and that he the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> ſhould be reſtored to his Eſtate and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But he anſwered; That he could prove no ſuch thing; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs they gave him time to conſider of it till the next day, which was the third and laſt day of his Tryal! <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which day the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> being brought into the Court, and urged again; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared again, that he never could prove any ſuch thing as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King: And added, that there were ſeveral Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages committed by Officers and others his aiders and abettors in the management of that War, contrary to his Intention, and which now preſſed his Conſcience very much; and that he could not in Conſcience had to them the unjust Calmniating the King, though he had been frequently ſolie<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ted thereunto by fair Promiſes and great Rewards while he was in Priſon. And proceeding further in this diſcourſe, that immediately he was ſtopt, before he had ended what he had further to ſay, the ſentence of death was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him.</p>
                           <p>And I do further declare, That I was preſent, and very near to the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> when he was upon the Ladder at his Execution; and that one Marſhal <hi>Peake,</hi> and another Marſhal, before the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> was caſt, came riding towards the place in great haſte, and called aloud, ſtop a little, and having paſſed through the throng of the ſpectators and guards, one of them whiſpered a prety while with the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> and that the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim</hi> anſwered in the hearing of ſeveral hundreds of People, of whom my ſelf was one, <hi>I thank the Lieutenant General for his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mercy, but I declare, good People, before God and his Holy Angels, and all of you that hear me, that I never had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Commiſſion from the King for what I have done, in Levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Proſecution of this War, and do heartily beg your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62608:20"/>Prayers all good Catholicks and Chriſtians, that God may be merciful unto me, and forgive me my ſins.</hi> More of his Speech I could not hear, which continued not long, the Guards beating off thoſe that ſtood near the place of Execution.</p>
                           <p>All that I have written as above, I declare to be true, and am ready if thereunto required, upon my Corporal Oath to atteſt the truth of every particular of it. And in Teſtimony thereof do hereunto Subſcribe my Hand, and affix my Seal, this 28th day of <hi>February, 1681.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>John Ker,</hi> Locus Sigilli.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>And now Reader, having vindicated the Honour, Piety, and all other Vertues of this Great Prince, from the Death-bed Declaration of one that was once his greateſt Enemy, having cleared the Truth of his Book, beyond Contradiction, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proved the Counterfeit <hi>Ludlow</hi> a great Lyar, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the King from the baſe and falſe Imputation of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, I have no more to ſay, than only to tell thee, That if the preſent Faction cannot employ a more modeſt and mannerly Champion, than this man is, I have done; for I do not love to be put to the trouble ſo often, of raking in ſinks and ſtinking dunghils, and if he wants employment, and will be Scribling again, I deſire him gravely and ſeriouſly, without railing and buffooning, to Anſwer theſe following Quaeries,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. Whether King <hi>Charles</hi> I. dyed by the hands of Juſtice, or was actually Murdered?</item>
                  <item>II. Whether thoſe that abet his Death now, are not ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually as guilty of it, as his Judges were?</item>
                  <item>III. Whether they that vindicate that Death, can be true and ſteady Subjects to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. Whether this mans and others aſſerting the Juſtice of the War againſt the King, and crying up his Death, be not to prepare the People to do the ſame thing againſt and upon others, when Time and Opportunity ſhall ſerve?</item>
                  <item>V. Whether he is to be believed in any thing he ſays, and does not deſerve a Pillory, that tells ſo horrid a Lye, as that the King ſent to Sir <hi>William Balfour</hi> to cut off the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62608:20"/>Lord <hi>Lowdens</hi> Head by Nine of the Clock next Morning, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Proceſs of Law?</item>
                  <item>VI. Whether he does not deſerve a ſevere Cenſure, that belyes my Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> with Words ſpoke at the Cabinet-Council, notwithſtanding the Marqueſs <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> Lord Treaſurer, and Lord <hi>Cottingten,</hi> upon their Honours declared, being preſent at the ſame Council, they heard no ſuch Words?</item>
                  <item>VII. Whether they are not great Fools, or deſigning K—that believe any thing this Libeller writes againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VIII. Whether he hath not done me a greater Honour than ever I could expect, or can deſerve, to belye, defame, and abuſe me, with the ſame Pen he has abus'd King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and that purely for His ſake?</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Whether that Holy and Renowned Martyr, Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and that ſtout Reformer <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> would not appear worſe Men, than this Scribler has made King <hi>Charles</hi> I. if we ſhould believe nothing of them, but what their grand Enemies the Prieſts and Jeſuites have writ againſt them.</item>
               </list>
               <p>After I had finiſhed the Defence of the King's Book, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this Letter from a Reverend Miniſter of <hi>Ipſwich</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> which deſerves to be taken Notice of.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SOME years after the Kings Tryal, Major <hi>Huntington</hi> at <hi>Ipſwich</hi> aſſured me, That ſo much of the ſaid Book as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained His Majeſties Meditations before <hi>Naſeby Fight,</hi> was taken in the Kings Cabinet, and that Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the ſaid Papers unto him, and ordered him to carry them to the King; and the Major affirmed, that he read them over before he delivered them, and that they were the ſame for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Form, with thoſe Meditations in the Printed Book, and that he was much affected with them, and from that time became a Proſelyte to the Royal Cauſe: He alſo told me, That when he delivered them to the King, His Majeſty appeared very joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62608:21"/>at the receiving of them, and ſaid he eſteemed them more than all the Jewels he had loſt in the Cabinet. Alſo I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, when I waited upon my Lord Vicount <hi>Hereford</hi> into <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (who was ſent by the Parliament with other Lords, to bring home King <hi>Charles II.</hi>) my Lord ſent me to Dr. <hi>Earl</hi> then at the <hi>Hague,</hi> to requeſt his Knowledge; whether the King was Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the ſaid Book, the Dr. told me, as ſure as he knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Tranſlator of it into Latin; ſo certain he was King <hi>Charles</hi> was the Author of the Original in Engliſh.</p>
                     <p>For my part, I am apt to believe no Perſon was able to frame that Book, but a Suffering King, and no Suffering King, but King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Humble Servant, <hi>Cave Becke.</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
